Religion is more than belief.
الدين أكثر من مجرد اعتقاد
It's power, and it's influence.
إنه السلطة والنفوذ.
And that influence affects all of us,
وهذا النفوذ يؤثر علينا جميعا،
every day, regardless of your own belief.
بشكل يومي و بغض النظر عن الدين خاصتك.
Despite the enormous influence of religion on the world today,
وعلى الرغم من التأثير الهائل للدين على العالم اليوم،
we hold them to a different standard of scrutiny and accountability
فإنَّنا نخضعه إلى معيار مختلف من التدقيق والمساءلة،
than any other sector of our society.
أكثر من أي قطاع آخر في مجتمعنا.
For example, if there were a multinational organization,
على سبيل المثال: إن كان هناك اليوم منظمة متعددة الجنسيات
government or corporation today
أو حكومة أو شركة،
that said no female could be on a leadership board,
تقول أنه لا يمكن لامرأة أن تكون في مجلس الإدارة،
not one woman could have a decision-making authority,
ولا امرأة لها الحق في سلطة اتخاذ القرار،
not one woman could handle any financial matter,
ولا يحق لامرأة التعامل مع أي مسألة مالية،
we would have outrage.
فسيتملّكنا الغضب.
There would be sanctions.
وستكون هناك عقوبات.
And yet this is a common practice in almost every world religion today.
ورغم ذلك، فهذه هي الممارسة الشائعة في كل أديان العالم اليوم تقريباً.
We accept things in our religious lives
فنحن نتفبّل أشياء في حياتنا الدينية
that we do not accept in our secular lives,
والتي لا نتقبّلها في حياتنا المدنية،
and I know this because I've been doing it for three decades.
وأنا أعلم هذا لأنني أفعله منذ 3 عقود.
I was the type of girl that fought every form of gender discrimination growing up.
كنت فتاة من النوع التي حاربت مختلف أشكال التمييز الجنسي خلال مسيرة حياتي.
I played pickup basketball games with the boys and inserted myself.
فقد لعبت مباريات كرة السلة مع الفتيان واندمجت مع الأمر.
I said I was going to be the first female President of the United States.
قلت بأني سأصبح أول امرأة تحكم الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية.
I have been fighting for the Equal Rights Amendment,
ظللت أقاتل من أجل تحسين الحقوق المتساوية،
which has been dead for 40 years.
والتي اندثرت منذ 40 عامًا.
I'm the first woman in both sides of my family
أنا أول امرأة على الإطلاق في كلي شقي أسرتي
to ever work outside the home and ever receive a higher education.
تعمل خارج المنزل وتتلقى تعليمًا عاليًا.
I never accepted being excluded because I was a woman,
لم أقبل إطلاقًا بأن يتم استثنائي بسبب كوني امرأة،
except in my religion.
ماعدا ما يمليه على ديني.
Throughout all of that time,
طوال كل هذا الوقت،
I was a part of a very patriarchal orthodox Mormon religion.
كنت جزءا من ديانة المورمون الأرثوذكسية البطريركية.
I grew up in an enormously traditional family.
ترعرعت في أسرة تقليدية جدًا.
I have eight siblings, a stay-at-home mother.
لي ثمانية أشقاء وأم ملازمة للبيت.
My father's actually a religious leader in the community.
في الواقع، أبي قائد ديني في الجماعة.
And I grew up in a world believing that my worth and my standing
وقد ترعرعت في عالم يؤمن بأن قيمتي ومكانتي
was in keeping these rules that I'd known my whole life.
تكمن في الالتزام بهذه القواعد التي تربيت عليها طيلة حياتي.
You get married a virgin, you never drink alcohol,
تتزوجين وأنت عذراء ولايسمح لك بتعاطي الكحول،
you don't smoke, you always do service,
يمنع عليك التدخين، تأدين خدمتك الدينية دائمًا،
you're a good kid.
وأن تظلي طفلة صالحة.
Some of the rules we had were strict,
كانت بعض القواعد التي يتوجب علينا اتباعها صارمة،
but you followed the rules because you loved the people
ولكنك تتبع التعاليم لأنك تحب الجماعة
and you loved the religion and you believed.
وتحب الدين ولأنك مؤمن به.
Everything about Mormonism determined what you wore,
تحدد العقيدة المورمونية بشكل كامل ما ترتديه من لباس،
who you dated, who you married.
من تواعد، بمن تتزوج،
It determined what underwear we wore.
حتى أنها تحدد نوع ملابسك الداخلية.
I was the kind of religious where everyone I know
بحكم انتمائي الديني، فكل شخص أعرفه
donated 10 percent of everything they earned to the church,
يهب 10% مما يكسب لصالح الكنيسة،
including myself.
بمن فيهم أنا.
From paper routes and babysitting, I donated 10 percent.
كنت أهب 10% مما أكسبه مقابل تسليم الصحف ومجالسة الأطفال
I was the kind of religious where I heard parents tell children
كنت متدينة حيث أسمع الآباء يقولون لأطفالهم
when they're leaving on a two-year proselytizing mission
وهم بصدد المغادرة في مهمة تبشير تمتد لسنتين
that they would rather have them die
أنهم يفضلون موتهم
than return home without honor, having sinned.
على أن يعودوا بلا شرف نتيجة الخطيئة.
I was the type and the kind of religious
كنت أنتمي لجماعة دينية
where kids kill themselves every single year
حيث ينتحر الأطفال كل سنة
because they're terrified of coming out to our community as gay.
بسبب أنهم مذعورون من التصريح على العلن بأنهم مثليون جنسيون.
But I was also the kind of religious
ولكن كنت أيضًا من النوع المتدين
where it didn't matter where in the world I lived,
حيث لم يكن يهم أن أعيش في العالم،
I had friendship, instantaneous mutual aid.
كان لي صداقة، وعون متبادل فوري.
This was where I felt safe. This is certainty and clarity about life.
هناك حيث شعرت بالأمان. مثل لي ذلك يقين ووضوح الحياة.
I had help raising my little daughter.
ساعدت في تربية أختي الصغيرة
So that's why I accepted without question that only men can lead,
لهذا السبب قبلت دون سؤال أن الرجال وحدهم بمقدورهم القيادة،
and I accepted without question
وقبلت دون سؤال
that women can't have the spiritual authority of God on the Earth,
أن النساء لايستطعن امتلاك السلطة الروحية لله على الأرض،
which we call the priesthood.
والتي ندعوها بالكهنوت.
And I allowed discrepancies between men and women in operating budgets,
وسمحت للتناقضات بين الرجال والنساء في الميزانيات التشغيلية،
disciplinary councils, in decision-making capacities,
والمجالس التأديبية، وفي إمكانية صنع القرار،
and I gave my religion a free pass
بعدها غضضت النظر عن ديني
because I loved it.
لأني أحببته.
Until I stopped,
حتى توقفت.
and I realized that I had been allowing myself to be treated
ثم أدركت أني سمحت بأن تتم معاملتي
as the support staff to the real work of men.
كفريق الدعم لعمل الرجال الحقيقي.
And I faced this contradiction in myself,
ولقد واجهت هذا التناقض داخلي،
and I joined with other activists in my community.
ثم انضممت إلى ناشطين آخرين في مجتمعي.
We've been working very, very, very hard for the last decade and more.
ظللنا نعمل جاهدين جدً جدًا جدًا خلال العقد الماضي أو يزيد.
The first thing we did was raise consciousness.
كان أول شيئ فعلناه هو رفع الوعي.
You can't change what you can't see.
فأنت لا تستطيع تغيير ما لا ترى.
We started podcasting, blogging, writing articles.
بدأنا البث على الإنترنت، والتدوين، وكتابة المقالات.
I created lists of hundreds of ways
ابتدعت قوائم تحوي مئات الطرق
that men and women are unequal in our community.
توضح كيف أن الرجال والنساء مختلفون في مجتمعنا.
The next thing we did was build advocacy organizations.
كان الشيئ التالي الذي فعلناه هو بناء منظمات تأييد.
We tried to do things that were unignorable,
حاولنا فعل أشياء لايمكن تجاهلها،
like wearing pants to church and trying to attend all-male meetings.
مثل ارتداء السراويل في الكنيسة ومحاولة حضور الاجتماعات المحصورة على الرجال.
These seem like simple things,
تبدو هذه كأشياء بسيطة،
but to us, the organizers, they were enormously costly.
ولكن بالنسبة لنا، نحن المنظمين، كانت تكلفة الأمر علينا باهضة.
We lost relationships. We lost jobs.
فقدنا علاقاتنا الاجتماعية. فقدنا وظائفنا.
We got hate mail on a daily basis.
كنا نتلقى رسائل الكراهية بوتيرة يومية.
We were attacked in social media and national press.
تعرضنا للهجوم على وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي والصحف القومية.
We received death threats.
تلقينا تهديدات بالتصفية.
We lost standing in our community. Some of us got excommunicated.
فقدنا مكانتنا وسط مجتمعنا. البعض منا تم حرمانهم كَنَسِيًا.
Most of us got put in front of a disciplinary council,
تم إخضاع معظمنا لمجلس تأديبي،
and were rejected from the communities that we loved
وتم رفضنا من قبل الجماعات التي أحببناها
because we wanted to make them better, because we believed that they could be.
بسبب أنا أردنا جعلهم أفضل، ولأنا آمنا أن بمقدورهم أن يصبحوا كذلك.
And I began to expect this reaction from my own people.
ثم بدأت أتوقع نفس الفعل من أهلي.
I know what it feels like when you feel like someone's trying to change you
أنا أعي مايبدو عليه الأمر عندما تشعر أن شخصا ما يحاول تغييرك
or criticize you.
أو انتقادك.
But what utterly shocked me was throughout all of this work
ولكن الشيئ الذي صدمني تمامًا طوال كل هذا العمل
I received equal measures of vitriol from the secular left,
هو أني تلقيت قدرًا من النقد اللاذع من اليسار العلماني،
the same vehemence as the religious right.
بنفس مقدار العنف من اليمين المتدين.
And what my secular friends didn't realize was that this religious hostility,
وما لم يلاحظه أصدقائي العلمانيون هو هذا العداء الديني،
these phrases of, "Oh, all religious people are crazy or stupid."
كعبارات من شاكلة: "أوه، كل الأشخاص المتدينون إما معتوهون أو أغبياء."
"Don't pay attention to religion."
"لا تولوا الدين اهتمامًا"
What they didn't understand
الشيئ الذي لم يفهموه
was that that type of hostility did not fight religious extremism,
هو أن هذا النوع من العداء لم يستهدف التطرف الديني
it bred religious extremism.
بلْ ولَّد التطرف الديني.
Those arguments don't work, and I know because I remember
هذه الحجج لا تفيد، وأنا أعي ذلك لأنِّي أتذكر
someone telling me that I was stupid for being Mormon.
قول شخص ما لي بأني كنت غبية لاعتناقي العقيدة المورمونية.
And what it caused me to do was defend myself and my people
وما حملني على ذلك هو الدفاع عن نفسي وعن أهلي
and everything we believe in, because we're not stupid.
و عن كل ما نؤمن به، لأنَّنا لسنا أغبياء.
So criticism and hostility doesn't work, and I didn't listen to these arguments.
إذا، النقد والعداء لا يجديان، وأنا لم ألق بالًا لهذه الحجج.
When I hear these arguments, I still continue to bristle,
فعندما أسمع هذه الحجج، أظل على موقف معاد لها،
because I have family and friends.
لأن لي عائلة وأصدقاء.
These are my people, and I'm the first to defend them,
هؤلاء هم أهلي، وسأكون في الطليعة للدفاع عنهم،
but the struggle is real.
ولكن النضال صعب.
How do we respect someone's religious beliefs
كيف لنا أن نحترم المعتقدات الدينية لشخص ما
while still holding them accountable for the harm or damage
بينما نحاسبهم على الأذى والضرر
that those beliefs may cause others?
الذي تسببه هذه المعتقدات للآخرين؟
It's a tough question. I still don't have a perfect answer.
إنه سؤال صعب. حتى الآن لا أملك له إجابة شافية.
My parents and I have been walking on this tightrope for the last decade.
ظللت أسير مع والدي على هذا الحبل المشدود طوال العقد الماضي.
They're intelligent people. They're lovely people.
إنهم أناس أذكياء ورائعون.
And let me try to help you understand their perspective.
ودعوني أحاول مساعدتكم على فهم وجهة نظرهم.
In Mormonism, we believe that after you die,
في المورمونية، نحن نؤمن أنه بعد الموت،
if you keep all the rules and you follow all the rituals,
إذا ما حافظت على القواعد، واتبعت كل التعاليم،
you can be together as a family again.
فسيكون بمقدورك أن تجتمع بعائلتك مجددًا.
And to my parents, me doing something as simple
وبالنسبة لوالدي، فكوني أفعل شيئًا بسيطًا
as having a sleeveless top right now, showing my shoulders,
كارتدائي لثوب بلا أكمام يظهر كتفي، كما الآن،
that makes me unworthy.
ذلك يجعلني غير جديرة.
I won't be with my family in the eternities.
فسوف لن أجتمع بعائلتي في الخلود.
But even more, I had a brother die in a tragic accident at 15,
ولكن أكثر من ذلك، توفي أخي في حادث حركة مأساوي وهو في سن 15 عامًا،
and something as simple as this means we won't be together as a family.
وشيئ بهذه البساطة يعني أنَّنا لن نجتمع كعائلة مجددًا.
And to my parents, they cannot understand
وبالنسبة لوالدي، فهما لا يستطيعان أن يفهما
why something as simple as fashion or women's rights
كيف أن شيئًا من البساطة بمكان مثل الموضة أو حقوق المرأة
would prevent me from seeing my brother again.
قد يمنعني من رؤية أخي مجددًا.
And that's the mindset that we're dealing with,
وتلك هي العقلية التي نتعامل معها،
and criticism does not change that.
والنقد ليس بوسعه أن يغير من ذلك.
And so my parents and I have been walking this tightrope,
لذلك ظللت وأبي نسير على هذا الحبل المشدود،
explaining our sides, respecting one another,
مفسرين لوجهات نظرنا، ومحترمين لبعضنا الآخر،
but actually invalidating each other's very basic beliefs
ولكن في الواقع، في حالة انكار لأبسط المعتقدات الأساسية لبعضنا البعض
by the way we live our lives, and it's been difficult.
ولكن الطريقة التي نمارس بها حياتنا ومازلنا هي طريقة صعبة.
The way that we've been able to do that
الطريقة التي اتبعناها لفعل ذلك
is to get past those defensive shells
هي أن ننفذ إلى ما خلف تلك القذائف الدفاعية
and really see the soft inside of unbelief and belief
حتى نتمكن بحق من رؤية الداخل المعتدل من الإيمان أو عدم الإيمان
and try to respect each other while still holding boundaries clear.
وأن نحاول احترام بعضنا البعض بينما نتمترس خلف الحدود بشدة.
The other thing that the secular left and the atheists and the orthodox
الشيئ الآخر الذي لم يفهمه اليسار العلماني والملحدون والأرثوذوكس
and the religious right, what they all don't understand
واليمين المتدين،
was why even care about religious activism?
هو لماذا نهتم أصلًا بالنشاط الديني؟
I cannot tell you the hundreds of people who have said,
لا يسعني أن أحصي لكم المئات من الناس الذين قالوا،
"If you don't like religion, just leave."
"إن كنت لا تحبين الدين، إذا غادري بسلام."
Why would you try to change it?
لماذا تحاولين تغييره؟
Because what is taught on the Sabbath
لأن ما يتم تدريسه في يوم العبادة
leaks into our politics, our health policy,
يتسرب إلى حياتنا السياسية، وسياستنا الصحية،
violence around the world.
وكذلك العنف حول العالم.
It leaks into education, military, fiscal decision-making.
يتسرب إلى التعليم والجيش واتخاذ القرارت المالية.
These laws get legally and culturally codified.
تصبح هذه القوانين مقننة و معروفة ثقافيًا.
In fact, my own religion has had an enormous effect on this nation.
في الحقيقة، كان لديني بالغ التأثير على هذه الأمة.
For example, during Prop 8, my church raised over 22 million dollars
على سبيل المثال، خلال الاقتراح الثامن جمعت كنيستي مبلغ 22 مليون دولار
to fight same-sex marriage in California.
لمحاربة زواج المثليين في ولاية كاليفورنيا.
Forty years ago, political historians will say,
منذ 40 سنة خلت، سيقول المؤرخون السياسيون،
that if it wasn't for the Mormon opposition to the Equal Rights Amendment,
أنه لولا المعارضة المورمونية لتحسين الحقوق المتساوية،
we'd have an Equal Rights Amendment in our Constitution today.
لكان هنالك تحسين للحقوق المتساوية ضمن دستورنا اليوم.
How many lives did that affect?
كم من الأرواح أثَّر عليها ذلك؟
And we can spend time fighting every single one
بمقدورنا قضاء الوقت نحارب كل واحدة على حدة
of these little tiny laws and rules,
من هذه القوانين والقواعد بالغة الصغر،
or we can ask ourselves,
أو بمقدرونا أن نسأل أنفسنا،
why is gender inequality the default around the world?
لماذا يعتبر عدم المساواة بين الجنسين هو الشيئ المسبق حول العالم؟
Why is that the assumption?
لماذا هذا الافتراض؟
Because religion doesn't just create the roots of morality,
بسبب أن الدين لا يخلق فقط جذور الأخلاق،
it creates the seeds of normality.
بل يخلق بذورالحالة الطبيعية أيضًا.
Religions can liberate or subjugate,
للأديان القدرة على التحرير أو الاستعباد،
they can empower or exploit, they can comfort or destroy,
بمقدورها التمكين أو الاستغلال، وبمقدورها المواساة أو التدمير،
and the people that tip the scales over to the ethical and the moral
والأشخاص الذين يقلبون الموازين المعنوية والأخلاقية
are often not those in charge.
غالبا ليسوا أولائك في القيادة.
Religions can't be dismissed or ignored.
الأديان لا يمكن استبعادها أو تجاهلها.
We need to take them seriously.
نحن بحاجة إلى أخذها على محمل الجد.
But it's not easy to influence a religion, like we just talked about.
لكن ليس من السهل أن نؤثرعلى الدين، كما تحدثنا توًا عن الأمر.
But I'll tell you what my people have done.
ولكن سأخبركم بما فعلته جماعتي.
My groups are small, there's hundreds of us,
جماعتي صغيرة في العدد، حيث يوجد المئات منا،
but we've had huge impact.
ولكن كان لنا تأثير عظيم.
Right now, women's pictures are hanging in the halls next to men
حاليًا، صور النساء معلقة على الجدران بجانب صورالرجال
for the first time.
للمرة الأولى.
Women are now allowed to pray in our church-wide meetings,
أصبح بمقدور النساء الآن أداء الصلاة في اجتماعات على مستوى الكنيسة،
and they never were before in the general conferences.
حيث لم يكن بمقدورهن ذلك في المؤتمرات العامة.
As of last week, in a historic move,
كما حدث الأسبوع الماضي، في خطوة تاريخية،
three women were invited down to three leadership boards
دعيت ثلاث نساء لشغل مناصب قيادية
that oversee the entire church.
الشيئ الذي تشرف عليه الكنيسة كلها.
We've seen perceptual shifts in the Mormon community
لقد شهدنا تحولات إدراكية في المجتمع المورموني
that allow for talk of gender inequality.
الشيئ الذي سمح بالحديث عن عدم المساواة بين الجنسين.
We've opened up space, regardless of being despised,
لقد أتحنا مساحة، على الرغم من كوننا مزدرين،
for more conservative women to step in and make real changes,
لمزيد من النساء المحافظات حتى يتمكن من الولوج وإحداث تغييرات حقيقية،
and the words "women" and "the priesthood" can now be uttered in the same sentence.
والآن أصبح بالإمكان نطق كلمة "نساء" و "الكهنوت" في عبارة واحدة.
I never had that.
لم أحظ بذلك من قبل.
My daughter and my nieces are inheriting a religion that I never had,
ترث ابنتي وبنات إخوتي دينًا لم أحظ بمثله،
that's more equal -- we've had an effect.
هو أكثر مساواة، حيث كان لنا تأثير.
It wasn't easy standing in those lines
لم يكن من السهل الوقوف ضمن تلك الصفوف
trying to get into those male meetings.
في محاولة الولوج إلى اجتماعات الرجال.
There were hundreds of us,
كان هناك المئات منا،
and one by one, when we got to the door,
وشيئًا فشيئًا، عندما وصلنا عند الباب،
we were told, "I'm sorry, this meeting is just for men,"
قيل لنا، "أنا آسف، هذا الاجتماع محصور على الرجال فقط."
and we had to step back and watch men get into the meeting
فتوجب علينا التراجع ومشاهدة الرجال وهم يدخلون إلى الاجتماع
as young as 12 years old,
بينما مر بنا صبي بعمر 12 سنة،
escorted and walked past us as we all stood in line.
مصحوبا بشخص آخر وتجاوزنا بينما نحن جميعا نقف في صف واحد.
But not one woman in that line will forget that day,
لن تنسى أي امرأة في ذلك الصف ذلك اليوم،
and not one little boy that walked past us will forget that day.
كما لن ينسى ذلك الصبي الصغير الذي تجازنا ذلك اليوم.
If we were a multinational corporation or a government, and that had happened,
إذا ما كنا شركة متعددة الجنسيات أو حكومة و حدث ذلك الأمر،
there would be outrage,
فسوف يكون هناك غضب،
but we're just a religion.
ولكنه مجرد دين.
We're all just part of religions.
نحن جميعنا جزء من الأديان.
We can't keep looking at religion that way,
لا يمكننا الاستمرار في النظر إلى الدين بتلك الطريقة،
because it doesn't only affect me, it affects my daughter
لأن تأثيره لا يقتصر علي فقط، بل يمتد إلى بنتي أيضًا
and all of your daughters and what opportunities they have,
وجميع بناتنا وفرصهم المستقبلية،
what they can wear, who they can love and marry,
ما يرتدينه، ومن يحببن ويتزوجن،
if they have access to reproductive healthcare.
وإذا ما كان بمقدورهن الحصول على الرعاية الصحية الإنجابية
We need to reclaim morality in a secular context
نحن بحاجة إلى إصلاح الأخلاق في سياق علماني
that creates ethical scrutiny and accountability
الشيئ الذي يخلق تمحيصًا ومحاسبةً أخلاقية
for religions all around the world,
لكل الأديان حول العالم،
but we need to do it in a respectful way
ولكننا بحاجة إلى فعل ذلك بطريقة محترمة
that breeds cooperation and not extremism.
تولد التعاون وليس التطرف
And we can do it through unignorable acts of bravery,
وبوسعنا فعل ذلك عن طريق تصرفات شجاعة من دون تجاهل،
standing up for gender equality.
دفاعًا عن المساواة بين الجنسين.
It's time that half of the world's population
حان الوقت لكي يحظى نصف سكان الأرض
had voice and equality within our world's religions,
بصوت وبالمساواة في أديان العالم،
churches, synagogues, mosques and shrines around the world.
في كل الكنائس والمعابد والمساجد والأضرحة حول العالم.
I'm working on my people. What are you doing for yours?
أنا أعمل من أجل تغيير أهلي، فماذا تعمل أنت لأهلك؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)